Now, we know how central bankers are
just itching to raise their policy rates
in response to oil, primarily those over
in Europe. But, it's not just Europe,
it's actually spreading. In fact, just
today, earlier today, an official from
the Bank of Korea said, "Hey, you know
what? Oil prices are up. Therefore, we
need to stop our rate cuts and start
thinking about rate hikes." We get all
that. But, what do the markets think?
What are markets actually pricing,
especially once we get out of the
short-run hawkishness from central
banks? What do the curves tell us about
what to expect from there? In a word,
frown.
There are clues about rate frowning
hidden on the yield curve, for example,
but it's not as easy nor straightforward
to decipher. But, this is where forward
rate markets come in. SOFR futures are
far from perfect, and to me, they're
significantly inferior to the old
eurodollar futures contracts, but for
our purposes, they'll do. Because when
you check the SOFR futures curve, that's
what you get, the frown. So, what is the
futures frown? Well, it's two parts that
add up to a single phrase which sends
chills up the spine of every official
central banker everywhere. Policy error.
And while that term is often misused by
the mainstream, it absolutely applies
here. The higher oil prices go in the
short run, the more likely both parts of
the futures frown come into play. First,
you got that hawkish itch, which will
only get stronger the higher petroleum,
gasoline, and diesel all go in the short
run. And the futures prices for those
keep pointing to, and I hate to use the
phrase, higher for longer on energy
costs. But, the real magic comes in the
second piece of that frown, and that has
been reshaped a couple times more
recently. But, also keep in mind as we
go forward, we're not just going to
focus exclusively on forward rates,
though that's where it's most easy to
see what we're talking about. Interest
rate swaps is another market, and it's
doing the same exact thing and adds up
to the same frownish future signal.
Now, before we get to SOFR and the
frown, let's do a quick update where the
energy shock really stands. Global oil
benchmarks are up sharply here on
Monday, led by Brent futures, which have
surged another 5%. Now, cash prices, as
we've gone over recently for various oil
types, they continue to be even higher
still. Over in the US, WTI futures, that
one is up 3 and 1/2% to 105.50.
It's the prompt spread on the futures
curve, which is the difference between
the front contract and the next one in
line. That one's about five bucks, and
the three-month spread, the benchmark
there is a little over $14. Now, these
spreads may be down from their most
extreme levels, but if not for, you
know, recently, today's spreads would be
at records. So, what they say is
that the oil market remains under
extreme duress with intense demand for
delivery at the nearest opportunities.
That's the, you know, cash spot market
but also the still rising chance the
shock sticks around even longer,
something that no one really wants.
That's especially true as the shock
translates into gasoline, diesel, and
other types of fuels that we actually
use. Wholesale gas over at the CME is up
to $3.73
a gallon as of this morning, continuing
to surge ahead of the WTI futures price.
That's not just the highest for RBOB
since 2022,
it's rapidly closing in on those highs
and threatening to surpass them. And
obviously, that would be bad news for
the economy everywhere, consumers most
of all. As I told you last month, energy
costs, primarily gasoline, are moving
closer to cash oil prices rather than
WTI futures in particular. And
naturally, the higher they all go, the
longer the energy marketplace stays this
way, we all know what's going to happen
across global central banks. Picture
Casey Jeff at the Fed huddled in the
corner of his office, sweating
profusely, screaming, "Remember Volcker!
Remember Volcker! Remember Volcker!"
That's only a slight embellishment, but
we know that central banks have shifted
more and more recently toward their
hawkish side. They see oil prices go up,
and they want to respond to them as if
they were Paul Volcker reincarnated.
Before we go on with our video today,
let me ask you a question. What if your
gold could actually pay you every single
month in more gold? That's what today's
video sponsor, Monetary Metals, lets you
do.
And here's how it works. You still own
the gold, it's still in your name, it's
fully insured, but instead of just
sitting there doing nothing, it actually
starts working for you. Monetary Metals
has built a system that turns idle gold
into productive gold, earning real yield
paid in physical gold, not dollars. No
selling, no trading, no converting. You
keep your gold, and every month, you get
more of it. It's a simple idea, but it
solves a big problem. If gold is money,
it should act like money, and now it
finally can.
If you're a long-term gold holder
looking for a smarter way to store
value, check them out at
monetary-metals.com/snyder.
Again, that's
I highly recommend booking a call with
them today to see if they're the right
fit for you. We thank Monetary Metals
for their sponsorship, but now, let's
get back to the rest of our video.
It's not just the Fed, it's being led by
Europe, and it's it's spreading around
the rest of the world. And you don't
have to take my word on it for this
part.
The higher oil goes, the more hawkish
most officials become because they can't
help themselves. We've seen countless
examples, starting recently with 2024,
the sticky inflation that wasn't, and of
course, 2022 itself. Don't forget 2008.
While these central bankers see
themselves as the reincarnation of Paul
Volcker, who, if you didn't know, he's
the former Fed chairman who we've been
told ended the Great Inflation, even
though nothing could have been further
from the truth, but what 2026's group of
central bankers are more likely
replaying is Jean-Claude Trichet, as
we'll see in the market curves. He's the
guy at the ECB who raised rates in the
middle of 2008 and then did it again in
the middle of 2011. Now, the reason why
there's this disconnect is the official
mainstream economics theory on
inflation. It's just garbage nonsense
absurdity, primarily based on what's
called expectations theory, which simply
says, once you, me, and everyone else
starts to see higher costs for things
across the economy, we begin to alter
our behavior expecting inflation to be
high into the future. We start buying
things today before the prices go up,
and that buying itself ends up being, or
at least heavily contributing to, the
inflation that we were afraid of in the
first place. And while it all sounds
plausible, there is no evidence for it
anywhere at any time. And policy makers,
they know this, too. Yet, they have no
choice but to stick with it because they
don't have any other clue or any other
alternative. As we know here at
Eurodollar University, officials have no
idea what's going on in the economy, let
alone in the monetary system, which is
where legitimate inflation comes from,
at least the kind that gets sustained.
So, they've incorporated expectations
theory into their econometric models,
and that's how they ended up with
Trichet, not just in 2008, as I said,
but also in 2011.
And as I've shown before, it wasn't only
the ECB back then. The Fed under Ben
Bernanke was this close, this close, to
following the Europeans in the middle of
2008. Can you imagine that? The guy said
subprime was contained in 2007, and then
if he did follow the ECB and raise rates
in the middle of 2008, I mean, I guess
they'd have to give him two Nobel Prizes
to cover everything up, to cover up the
shame.
So, at the Federal Reserve meeting last
week, the vote to pause rates right
where they are produced the most
dissents the committee has seen in over
30 years. Now, we still had the one
dissent from Mester, who wants a rate
cut, but now you've got three dissents.
They're not necessarily agitating for a
rate hike, they just don't want the Fed
to outright state that they think their
next move is going to be a rate cut. So,
it's slightly more hawkish than they had
been at the previous meeting in March.
And that was Cleveland, Barr, Dallas,
Logan, and Neel. Keep in mind, Casey
Jeff, he probably would have dissented,
but he doesn't get a vote this year.
But, you can bet he was right there
egging them on. So, not overly hawkish,
but a visible shift in that direction at
the Federal Reserve. Now, over in
Europe, the ECB has laid the groundwork
for a hike at its next meeting in June.
The same for the Bank of England. The
Bank of Japan ended up with a similar
split to the Fed, moving more in the
same direction. And another one that's
now itching for hawks is South Korea.
One voter from that country's central
bank policy committee said earlier today
that prices are facing, \quote}
significant upward pressure, thanks,
Captain Obvious, and that, \quote} it's
time to consider stopping rate cuts and
thinking about increases. And we could
go on and on with examples. The global
balance has shifted out of the Pringles
can, but only temporarily. That's the
key here. It is, to use their word,
transitory. Now, everyone knows the
economy's facing significant upward
pressure on prices. That's not the issue
here. It's what that significant upward
pressure becomes, runaway inflation or
the other historically consistent option
the markets and at least few central
bankers are seeing as more likely.
That's the frown. The world's officials
all go full on Trichet over oil and
expectations theory, but then realize a
little later on it was a big mistake,
the policy error. They didn't produce
the downside, they were wrong about the
inflation upside from the very
beginning. It's not like their rates go
too high and cause the recession. They
make The error is them assuming higher
oil prices end up being inflationary,
requiring policy rates to move up in the
first place. Oil shocks become
recessions, not great inflations. So,
knowing that, and also knowing how badly
central bankers want to Trichet
themselves as the higher oil prices go,
what shape do you think the forward rate
market would take, the forward rate
curve, SOFR What shape should the SOFR
futures curve be understanding both
parts of the central bankers in the near
term and then the long run likelihoods
beyond it. Not even long run,
intermediate likelihoods beyond it. What
curve shape would you expect from SOFR
futures? It would be a frown.
The market is forecasting a decent
non-zero chance that even the Federal
Reserve might jump in on the rate hiking
at some point. Thus, it's upward sloping
in the relatively near term. But since
that's an error, a mistaken interpreting
the danger of oil prices and what they
really represent, they're downward
sloping into next year. So, rates go up
and then come right back down. And keep
in mind, the curve was sharply sharply
inverted still before the Iran conflict
began on February 27th, which is the
last day before the missiles really
started flying and the ships stopped
shipping, look at how steeply inverted
SOFR futures had been. That was a
combination of flat beverage worries and
private credit. Both of those
increasingly likely to force the FOMC,
even the KC Jeff gang, back into the
Pringles can at some point, probably
later this year. Now, starting March 2nd
as the Iran conflict erupted,
oil surged, SOFR futures were hit hard.
In other words, the forward rate market
knew exactly what had changed and it
wasn't inflation prospects. Everyone
knew officials wouldn't be able to
resist becoming Trichet. Contract hedges
were taken out and were bought against
the shifts among central banker
boardrooms, not out there in the real
economy. That's why even those early
days in March as oil and gasoline
jumped, the frown developed. It was all
about a short-term reverse in short-term
rates driven by policy makers stricken
by Volker fever fantasies. But then look
what happened once the oil prices
slacked off in the first half of April.
The upward slope at the front of the
frown disappeared and the curve almost
almost went back to fully inverted, the
same fully inverted shape from late
February. Again, the market isn't
changing its outlook on the economy,
it's changing how it interprets how
central bankers will interpret oil. And
over the last couple of weeks with
energy prices surging again, the frown
has come roaring back. But notice how it
isn't nearly as frowny as it been back
in March. That's the market downgrading
the Trichet tendency despite central
bankers statements and indications
showing they're even more hawkish today
than they were not all that long ago.
Because that's the final variable in the
frown. Just how much runway central
bankers might actually have to play act
Volker. If the economy falls off more
quickly, and the higher oil prices go,
the more likely that becomes, then they
flip from short run hikes to Pringles
even faster, which means there aren't as
many rate hikes in the short run and the
return of cutting rates comes much
sooner and develops even faster. They
all think they're being Volker when the
markets are consistently pricing total
Trichet.
Now, as I said in the introduction here,
it's not just forward rate markets. We
can see the same interpretation out of
interest rate swaps and interest rate
swap spreads.
They're right there with forward rates.
So, it's not as clear and visually
obvious like it is for SOFR futures and
the frown. You look at the curve and you
immediately understand what that means.
Rates go up a little bit in the short
run, then go back down and maybe a lot
farther not too far down the road. Now,
swap spreads looking at everything the
same way. Those were compressing again
from late in January, which is the same
combination of flat beverage and blue
owl that had the SOFR curve steeply
inverted. The more negative swap spreads
represent the same thing as a heavily
inverted forward rate curve. The
expectation that short-term rates are
going to go down and probably by a lot.
Now, where swap spreads take this even
further is by adding another time
dimension to it. In this case, rates go
down just like SOFR futures. They go
down by a lot just like SOFR futures
before March, but then they stay there
for a long time. That's the verdict and
prediction and forecast from the swap
spread market. And that didn't change
with the energy shock. If anything,
spreads kept compressing further as oil
and gasoline really started to pick up.
The swap market looking into the future
and seeing the historical energy shock
case take shape. And in April, that did
back off a little bit in the swap
market. Spreads decompressed a little,
meaning became less negative with oil
coming down. So, maybe not as much
economic damage and recession leading to
panicky central bankers having to cut as
far as they would have or taking a
little bit longer to get there. That's
probably the more likely scenario. But
by and large, the swap market didn't
really change up throughout the energy
shock the entire way so far, moving back
closer to last year's extremely negative
spreads. That's not central bankers
raising rates a lot because of oil
leading to out of control inflation. It
is officials getting a rate hike, maybe
two in there before realizing they
messed up again and having to do what
they were going to be forced to do
before March and the Iran conflict.
Swaps are right there with SOFR futures
and the SOFR futures curve frown.
And we should also note because markets
sure do, that there are counterbalances
out there among all the Trichets running
around, the hawkish central banks.
Central bank committees are not
monolithic. There are sane and rational
voices out there. I mean, after all, the
Federal Reserve, while there were four
dissenters and three the hawkish
variety, that left eight, the majority,
to suggest what the markets are. That
there is a historical case for, okay, we
don't really know what's going on oil
prices. We're We're sympathetic to the
expectations theory argument, but
however, we also know we remember what
happened in 2008. We also know the
historical case on the energy shock. So,
a lot of officials, while the hawks get
all the noise, a lot of officials are,
hey, we don't really know which way to
turn. Some of them are indeed aware
expectations theory is questionable, to
put it charitably, how historically
energy shocks lead to recession. And
that there really are way too many
similarities to Jean-Claude Trichet
right now. And the best example of this
reasonable rational take is our
neighbors up in Canada. I pointed this
out last week, too, how the Bank of
Canada is quote looking through oil
prices right now, understanding how
there will be a short run impact from
gasoline to CPIs, but that there aren't
any indications, starting with
historical precedent, to believe
anything else.
But because the economy's already weak
up there to begin with, just look at the
Canadian labor market, officials should
not and really cannot overlook that
downside case, the other side, the far
side of the futures frown. Even over
there in Europe, where the insanity has
been dialed up, there are a few sane
voices. Maybe it's just like they seem
sane by comparison to all the hawk
crazies, but here's one, well, at least
one example from already earlier today
amidst all this Trichet fever. Quote,
"Concerned about a possible Eurozone
recession is real and justified as
conflict in the Middle East causes a
supply side disruption." European
Central Bank Governing Council member
Yannis Stournaras
said in an interview with another Greek
word I can't pronounce.
The guy who heads the Bank of Greece
told the Cyprus-based outlet, "There's
no sign of significant pass-through of
higher energy prices to inflation,
though it's too early for precise
estimates." Now, his colleague at the
ECB, Olli Rehn, also admitted there are
quote, "No obvious signs of second order
effects." We talked about second order
effects just earlier, on broad consumer
prices. That's when energy costs go up
and force the prices of non-energy goods
and services to rise as a result. And
that's where the whole argument has
been. We know energy costs are going up
and it's going to contribute something,
but is it going to lead to runaway
inflation in an even broader set of
consumer goods?
But this whole argument is one that
should be very familiar to everyone.
It's exactly what these same Trichets
had said would happen last year from
tariffs when, once again, it was more
the opposite than not. Tariffs push up
the cost of materials and some goods,
but it didn't lead to runaway or even
detectable acceleration in broad
consumer prices. Companies wanted to
raise what they charged consumers, but
in example after example, what happened
instead? Those who tried lost a ton of
volume and many of them ended up pulling
their prices back down all over again.
We went over Pepsi, McDonald's, all of
those. Worse, as those businesses
absorbed higher tariff-induced input
costs, it squeezed their margins a
little bit more than they had been,
convincing employers to cut back on
employment. It didn't lead to inflation.
Tariffs made the flat beverage labor
market a little bit flatter. The energy
shock is far far more likely to do the
same and in a much bigger way as the
frown in the forward rate market and on
the Greek ECB guy all show.
Now, the Treasury or any of the global
government bond markets are pricing the
same thing as forward rates and interest
rate swaps. It's just that they're much
harder to see it see clearly because you
end up having to parse the flatness of
positive spreads. So, we got to give it
to flawed SOFR futures here. You want an
easy visual of an energy shock and its
two likely effects on short-term rates,
look no further than the frown. First,
central bankers go crazy thinking Volker
over inflation when it's just oil. Then
they realize later on they Trichet'd
themselves and are heading back toward
the historical energy shock case. The
frown is not only a perfect
visualization of that process, it also,
unfortunately,
fits the circumstances.
And it's not just Canadian central
bankers that are sounding sane, the
behavior of European banks. Not European
central banks, but European banks also
consistent with the frown. That's in the
video link below. As always, thank you
very much for joining me. Huge thank
you, Euro Dollar University members and
subscribers. And until next time, take
care.